Jane M. Oppenheimer Papers 1936-1962 Mss.B.Op5
American Philosophical Society
Jane M. Oppenheimer Papers
1936-1962
Mss.B.Op5
American Philosophical Society
0.25 Linear feet
The embryologist and historian of science Jane M. Oppenheimer was a graduate and long term member of the faculty at Bryn Mawr College. Her research centered on the early development of the killifish Fundulus heteroclitus and on the history of embryology. The Oppenheimer Papers are a small collection consisting of Oppenheimer's correspondence with a small number of colleagues regarding her publications in the history of science and medicine and various other topics. With one exception, all letters in the collection are addressed to Oppenheimer.
Oppenheimer, Jane M., (Jane Marion), 1911-
Related Archival Materials note
Oppenheimer also appears as a correspondent in the papers of Warren H. Lewis (B L586).
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of Jane M. Oppenheimer, 1987 (accn. no. 1987-858ms).
Scope and Contents note
The Jane M. Oppenheimer Papers are a small collection consisting of Oppenheimer's correspondence with a small number of colleagues regarding her publications in the history of science and medicine and various other topics. With one exception, all letters in the collection are addressed to Oppenheimer.
Biographical/Historical note
The embryologist Jane M. Oppenheimer was born in Philadelphia on September 19, 1911, and received her bachelors' degree in Zoology from Bryn Mawr College in 1932. She entered graduate school at Yale under the direction of John Spangler Nicholas, receiving her PhD in 1935 for a dissertation on the embryology of the killifish Fundulus heteroclitus in which she developed a novel methodology for dechorionating the embryo, making precise experimental manipulations of teleost embryos possible.
Oppenheimer returned to Bryn Mawr in 1938 as an instructor in biology, and remained there until her retirement in 1980, eventually rising to become William R. Kenan, Jr., Professor of Biology and History of Science. Perhaps her most important work was done in the four years immediately prior to her arrival at Bryn Mawr, when she performed a series of grafting experiments that demonstrated homology between the dorsal lips of teleost and amphibian embryos. She also developed accurate fate maps of the teleost embryo blastoderm and charted cell movement in gastrulation.
Early in her career, Oppenheimer developed an interest in the history of science and medicine, and she became increasingly well known for her contributions in the history of embryology and evolutionary biology. Her major works include Autobiography of Karl Ernst von Baer (Canton, Mass., 1986), Foundations of Experimental Embryology (Englewood Cliffs, N.J., 1964), and Essays in the History of Embryology and Biology (Cambridge, Mass., 1967).
Oppenheimer was elected to the American Academy of Arts and Letters and, in 1980, to the APS, serving as Secretary from 1987 to 1992. She was recipient of the Otto H. Hafner Award of the American Association of the History of Medicine, the Karl Ernst von Baer Medal from the Estonian Academy of Sciences, the Wilbur Lucius Cross Medal from the Yale Graduate Alumni Association, and the Christian R. and Mary F. Lindback Award for distinguished teaching at Bryn Mawr. She died at age 84 on March 19, 1996.
Cushing, Harvey, 1869-1939; Frisch, Karl von, 1886-1982; Harrison, Ross G., (Ross Granville), 1870-1959; Tennent, David Hilt, 1873-; Todd, Thomas Wingate, 1885-; Ubisch, Leopold von, 1886-1965; White, E. B. (Elwyn Brooks), 1899-; Embryology--History; Women embryologists
- Jane M. Oppenheimer Papers, 1936-1962; 0.25 lin. feet (Box 1)
  - TLsS to Jane M. Oppenheimer, 1936-1939; 11 items; Cushing, Harvey, 1869-1939
    Scope and Contents note
    Re: publications and research in history of embryology.
    - TLS to Jane M. Oppenheimer, 1936 February 14; 1p.; Cushing, Harvey, 1869-1939
    - TLS to Jane M. Oppenheimer, 1936 March 6; 1p.; Cushing, Harvey, 1869-1939
    - TLS to Jane M. Oppenheimer, 1936 April 27; 1p.; Cushing, Harvey, 1869-1939
    - TLS to Jane M. Oppenheimer, 1936 August 10; 1p.; Cushing, Harvey, 1869-1939
    - TLS to Jane M. Oppenheimer, 1936 October 23; 1p.; Cushing, Harvey, 1869-1939
    - TLS to Jane M. Oppenheimer, 1936 December 10; 1p.; Cushing, Harvey, 1869-1939
    - TLS to Jane M. Oppenheimer, 1937 January 7; 1p.; Cushing, Harvey, 1869-1939
    - TLS to Jane M. Oppenheimer, 1937 July 29; 1p.; Cushing, Harvey, 1869-1939
    - TLS to Jane M. Oppenheimer, 1939 May 22; 1p.; Cushing, Harvey, 1869-1939
    - TLS to Jane M. Oppenheimer, 1939 July 22; 1p.; Cushing, Harvey, 1869-1939
    - ALS to Jane M. Oppenheimer, n.d.; 1p.; Cushing, Harvey, 1869-1939
  - TLsS to Jane M. Oppenheimer, 1959-1962; 11 items; Frisch, Karl von, 1886-1982
    General note
    in German
    - TLS to Jane M. Oppenheimer, 1959 March 19; 1p.; Frisch, Karl von, 1886-1982
    - TLS Cy to Karl von Frisch, 1959 March 19; 1p.; Oppenheimer, Jane M., (Jane Marion), 1911-
    - TLS to Jane M. Oppenheimer, 1959 April 20; 1p.; Frisch, Karl von, 1886-1982
    - TLS to Jane M. Oppenheimer, 1959 July 19; 1p.; Frisch, Karl von, 1886-1982
    - TLS to Jane M. Oppenheimer, 1959 October 7; 1p.; Frisch, Karl von, 1886-1982
    - TLS to Jane M. Oppenheimer, 1959 October 31; 2p.; Frisch, Karl von, 1886-1982
    - TLS to Jane M. Oppenheimer, 1960 April 16; 1p.; Frisch, Karl von, 1886-1982
    - TLS to Jane M. Oppenheimer, 1960 May 3; 1p.; Frisch, Karl von, 1886-1982
    - TLS to Jane M. Oppenheimer, 1960 July 25; 1p.; Frisch, Karl von, 1886-1982
    - TLS to Jane M. Oppenheimer, 1960 August 8; 1p.; Frisch, Karl von, 1886-1982
    - TLS to Jane M. Oppenheimer, 1962 May 4; 1p.; Frisch, Karl von, 1886-1982
  - ALsS to Jane M. Oppenheimer, 1938-1955; 3 items; Harrison, Ross G., (Ross Granville), 1870-1959
    - Postcard to Jane M. Oppenheimer, 1938 March 20; 1p.; Harrison, Ross G., (Ross Granville), 1870-1959
    - TLS to Jane M. Oppenheimer, 1942 March 28; 1p.; Harrison, Ross G., (Ross Granville), 1870-1959
    - ALS to Jane M. Oppenheimer, 1947 March 9; 1p.; Harrison, Ross G., (Ross Granville), 1870-1959
    - ALS to Jane M. Oppenheimer, 1955 March 24; 1p.; Harrison, Ross G., (Ross Granville), 1870-1959
  - TLS to Jane M. Oppenheimer, 1938; 1 item; Tennent, D. H.
    - ALS to Jane M. Oppenheimer, 1938 May 10; 2p.; Tennent, D. H.
  - TLS to Jane M. Oppenheimer, 1937; 1 item; Todd, T. Wingate
    - ALS to Jane M. Oppenheimer, 1937 August 13; 2p.; Todd, T. Wingate
  - TLsS to Jane M. Oppenheimer, 1960; 2 items; Ubisch, Leopold von
    - TLS to Jane M. Oppenheimer, 19; 3p.; Ubisch, Leopold von
      In German. Includes TMs "Märachen."
  - TLS to Jane M. Oppenheimer, 1947; 1 item; White, E. B.
    - TLS to Jane M. Oppenheimer, 19; 1p.; White, E. B.